A Guide to the IAWA Small Collections, 1907-2013
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
- Persons and Associations
  - Campana, Ana, biographical material, 1987, 1994, and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born 1934 in Cuba. Senior architect for the General Electric Company since 1974, specializing in the design of power plant facilities. Collection consists of a curriculum vitae and biography, and copies of certificates from Who's Who in the World and Who's Who of American Women.
  - Cardenas, Eliana, publications, 1999, 2002, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Eliana Maria Cardenas Sanchez is a Cuban architect and architectural historian. This collection includes two issues of the journal arquitectura y urbanismo, 2/1999 and 3/2002, each of which contain articles by Cardenas and a university textbook, Un siglo de enseñanza de la arquitectura en Cuba, that she helped edit [NA2151 .I67 2002]. Additional publications by Cardenas are also available in the book collection through the VT library's online catalog, Addison.
  - Carlini, Erdmute, papers, 1977, 1980-1989, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born 1941. Landscape architect of Berlin, Germany. Materials include two catalogs, Berlin/Los Angeles: Working Together in Culture, Science and Industry--Fantasy and Realism in Architecture, about an exhibition of the Werkbund Berlin at UCLA in which Carlini showed her work, and Dan Markische Viertel-25 Jahre Danach, by Carlini and her husband; postcards of her work; and catalogs (1977-1989) in which her work is cited. Ms2000-024.
  - Chestnutt, Rebecca, catalog, 2000, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born in Spartanburg, South Carolina, Chestnutt received her Master of Architecture degree from Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University in 1981. In 1983 she moved to Berlin and by 1988 Chestnutt started her firm with Robert Niess, a colleague from Virginia Tech. The collection includes a copy of the catalog, The History of Air 1988-2000, showing three of their buildings. Inventory available.
  - Chowdhury, Urmile Eulie, biographical material, 1965 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born 1923. Architect of Chandigarh, India; first woman to qualify as an architect in Asia and to be Chief Architect of an Indian state (Punjab). Materials include a curriculum vitae and copies of letters sent by the architect Le Corbusier in the 1960s.
  - Chin, Sho-Ping, scholarship announcement 2016, Extent: 0.1 cu. ft. (Box 20)
    Architect of Boston, Massachusetts. Sho-Ping Chin FAIA (1953-2015) was a Principal at Payette, specializing in healthcare architecture. A founding member of the AIA Women's Leadership Summit and active member of the Boston Society of Architects, Sho-Ping advocated passionately on behalf of Women in Design. In January 2016, Payette announced the Payette Sho-Ping Chin Memorial Academic Scholarship, a $10,000 annual award for a woman studying architecture at the undergraduate and graduate level. The award was the first AIA Scholarship named after a woman architect and the first specifically designated for women students. Materials comprise an email about the scholarship's creation and a copy of the 2016 scholarship announcement.
  - Christianovic, Ruth, papers, 1974, 1987-1989, Extent: 0.4 cubic feet (Box 10, Oversize 22)
    Born 1923. Architect and artist of Vienna, Austria. Materials consist of a résumé and architectural plans of her designs, sketches, and watercolors of landscapes and buildings.
  - Ciocãnea, Doina Marilena, papers, 1999, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 10)
    Born 1951 in Bucharest, Romania, where she received her diploma in 1976 from the Institute of Architecture. Papers consist of a résumé, photographs and photocopies of drawings of portions of her work. Inventory available.
  - Cline, Ann, articles, 1989-1997, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Artist and architect of California and Ohio; Associate Professor of Architecture at Miami University in Oxford, Ohio. Materials consist of articles by Cline and about Cline's work on "Little Houses" or one-room spaces, and an exhibit of her work at Miami University in 1989.
  - Cole, Doris, papers, 1991-2004, 2006 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    President/Director of the firm Cole and Goyette, Architects and Planners, in Cambridge, Massachusetts, and a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects (FAIA). Collection includes brochure packets from her firm and postcards showing her work. A signed copy of her 1973 book, From Tipi to Skyscraper: A History of Women in Architecture and a copy of her new book Candid Reflections: Letters from Women in Architecture 1972 and 2004 (2007) are cataloged in ADDISON and available in the Special Collections Rare Book Room.
  - Colter, Mary, media collection, 1996, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    1869-1958. Chief architect for the Fred Harvey Company. Designed hotels, gift shops, and viewing places throughout the southwestern desert in the United States in the early 1900s. Her most notable designs were the Watchtower, Hopi House, and Hermit's Rest at the Grand Canyon National Park in Arizona. Collection includes film entitled "Mary Jane Colter: The Desert View" produced, written, and directed in 1996 by Jennifer Lee of Beverly Hills, California, and narrated by Ellen Burstyn, about Colter's life and work. [Circulating copy available at Art/Arch Library: Video 5508.] Also available are National Public Radio program cassettes 526/527 in Rare Book Room.
  - Constructive Women Architecture and Design Archive newsletters, 1994-2003, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    An archive located in North Sydney, Australia, of images of work by women architects and designers in Australia, formed in 1995. Records consist of a cover letter introducing the archive, a general information and collection policy form, guidelines for submitting work to the archive form, a biographical questionnaire, an image documentation form, and a copyright agreement form. Also includes issues of Constructive Times, a newsletter of the Association of Women Architects, Landscape Architects, Planners and Women in the Building Industry, in Australia.
  - Cooper, Margaret Robb Shook "Robbie," curriculum vitae and brochure, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born 1925 in Tuscaloosa, Alabama. Partner of Architecture 2, a firm in Washington, D.C. Materials include a curriculum vitae and a brochure, "Robbie Cooper Design."
  - Cornelius, Ulla, architectural drawings, 1983-1985, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born 1952. Architect of Munster, Germany. The collection consists of four architectural designs.
  - Cutler, Sherrie S., brochure, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Architect of Cambridge, Massachusetts. Collection consists of a brochure about her firm, Ecodesign International.
  - DeGezelle, Molly, invention papers, 1991-1994, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born in 1979, resident of Mankato, Minnesota. Invented a building material composed of recycled paper and glue, originally created as an entry in a science fair competition in 1991. The material is now manufactured under the trade name Environ, by Phoenix Biocomposites. Collection consists of literature about the invention, including the paper she wrote for the science fair, biographical information about DeGezelle, and samples of her original invention (which she called "MollyBoard") and Environ.
  - Delavrancea-Gibory, Henriette, biographical material, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Three page biographical sketch with project list, author unknown, undated
  - Demi, Engjellushe Hoxha, CD, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Collection consists of a mini-CD with computer drawings by architect Engjellushe Hoxha Demi.
  - Diaz, Luz Maria Beristain, thesis, 1996, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    A member of the Faculty of Architecture at the Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Mexico, Division de Postgrado, The collection consist of Beristain Diaz's Master's Thesis in Restoration of Monuments entitled "Restoration of the Barrio de Tizapan Historical Center, Mexico City." Inventory available online.
  - Dietrich, Verena, papers, 1980-1986, 1992, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born 1941. Architect of Cologne, Germany. Papers include photographs of Dietrich and of her designs, a list of her designs from 1979 to 1990, copies of architectural drawings and photographs for her book, Architecktinnen: Ideen-Projekte-Bauten 1986, a exhibition poster of her work in Berlin (1992), and articles (1980-86) by her and about her work.
  - Dombai, Dr. Maria, biographical material and presentation panels, 2003, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 14)
    Architect of Budapest, Hungary. Dombai began her professional life in a planning office for the Hungarian food industry. She also taught at the university level and was a manager for the construction of a church-complex, and an architectural advisor for the National Association of Large Families (which addressed housing policy). The collection includes a biographical statement by Dombai, a photograph of Dombai, and a series of 9 panels presenting several of her projects from 1962-1986.
  - Donev, Miriana, résumé, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Architect of New Rochelle, New York; job captain of the firm of Allan Greenberg, Architect, of New Haven, Connecticut. Graduated from the Parsons School of Design in 1975 (B.F.A. in Environmental Design) and Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University in 1977 (M. Arch.). Curriculum vitae.
  - Dougherty, Betsey Olnick, papers, 1980-1986, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Architect of Newport Beach, California. Member of the National American Institute of Architects Board of Directors representing California, and a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Papers consist of photographs (1980-86) of her designs and a flyer and a brochure of her firm, Dougherty + Dougherty.
  - Dow, Joy Wheeler, article, 1982, Extent: 0.1 cu.ft. (Box 11)
    Photocopy of a design by Joy Wheeler Dow, an architect in New Jersey, published in County and Suburban Homes of the Prairie School Period 1982.
  - Drew, Jane, obituary, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Born 1911, died 1996. Assistant Town Planning Advisor to the Colonies of Nigeria, the Gold Coast, Sierra Leone, and Gambia.
  - Driskel, Jean Roth papers, 1949-1958, 1968-1971, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 2)
    1915-1971. Fellow of the American Institute of Architects, member of the Union Internationale des Femmes Architectes, and national president (1954-1956) of the Association of Women in Architecture. Designer of residential, commercial, and industrial buildings in Pasadena, California. Collection includes notebook of material relating to Driskel and her career, including a photograph, correspondence regarding her membership in the American Institute of Architects (1949-1958), news clippings (1968-1971), and obituaries, donated by the Association for Women in Architecture. Also has materials on VT Imagebase.
  - Enriquez-Musni, Marjorie L., curriculum vitae, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Born 1958. Planner of Manila, the Philippines. Materials consist of her curriculum vitae.
  - Fallon, Kristine K., papers, 1979-2013, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Born 1949. Former president of Computer Technology Management, Inc., of A. Epstein Companies, in Chicago, Illinois, and a consultant to architects and engineers on the effective use of computers in facility design. Current head of Kristine Fallon Associates, Inc. Collection materials consist of a résumé, a career information form from the AIA Archives, materials from the UIFA 1979 conference and essays. UIFA materials include a program, a participant's list, and two papers, "Computer-Aided Design in Architectural Practice" by Fallon and "If the City Were a She" by Donna E. Shalala. Essays include a 1980 article by Fallon, "An Overview of Computer Aided Design in Architectural Practice," a 1981 article by Margrit Kennedy, "Gyn/Ecology: On the Relationship Between Woman/ Nature/Space," a 1988 article, "Computer Applications in Building Design and Management" in which Fallon is featured, and a 2002 book, "Leading the Digital Practice: The A/E/C Firm Manager's Guide to Information Technology" co-authored by Fallon and Arleen Boyd. A digital copy of KFA's 2004 report for the Art Institute of Chicago, "Collecting, Archiving, and Exhibiting Digital Design Data" is also included.
  - Fessas-Emmanouil, Helen, biographical work, 2004, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Architect and professor in Athens, Greece. Author of Public Architecture in Modern Greece, 1827-1992 and Essays on Neohellenic Architecture, which are available in the library catalog, Addison. Ms2004-011
  - Figueira, Leonor curriculum vitae, 1987, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Born 1937. Principal architect of the Portuguese Institute of Cultural Heritage. Curriculum vitae prepared by the United States Information Agency.
  - Filas, Hilde, brochure, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Architect of Vienna, Austria. Brochure of her work.
  - Fisher, Laura A. Horstman, biographical material, 1986, 2002 1986, 2002 1986, 2002, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Vice president of facilities at Allied Bancshares, Inc. in Houston, Texas. Member of the American Institute of Architects, FAIA. Collection includes a résumé and biography; an article citing her as the recipient of the 1986 Young Architect Award from the Houston AIA; a catalog she edited, Houston's Gallery of Architecture: A Walking Tour of Downtown Houston, and her nomination binder for AIA Fellowship.
  - Flagge, Ingeborg, catalog, 1987, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Architect of Bonn, Germany. Flagge edited the catalog entitled "Frauen in der Architektur--bauen Frauen anders?" (Women in Architecture - Do Women Build Differently?) that arose from a discussion at the Friedrick-Ebert-Stiftung in 1987.
  - Flecken, Ursula, architectural drawings, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 14)
    Architect of Aachen, Germany. Papers consist of two sets of architectural drawings, "The Reorganization of the Central Area of Monchengladbach" and "Improvement of the 'Märkisches Viertel' in Berlin."
  - Forsthuber, Sabine, papers, 1985-1993, Extent: 0.4 cubic feet (Box 12)
    Art and architecture historian of Vienna, Austria. Papers consist of literature about prominent women architects of Austria, including Anne-Lulja Praun and Margarette Schutte-Lihotzky. Also includes an article Forsthuber wrote about the history of women architects in Austria.
  - Fritz, Sylvia, papers, 1981-1987, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Born in 1955 in Vienna, Austria, Fritz is an architect and artist. Materials include a brochure of Fritz's work from 1977 to 1987; photographs of her; an exhibition leaflet, Turme von Sylvia Fritz (1982); and articles (1981-1984) in which her work is cited.
  - Gabrea, Georgeta, papers, 1996-1999, Extent: 0.25 cubic feet (Box 19)
    Born 1953 in Bucharest, Romania. Officer of architectural firm, Capitel Limited. Papers consist of a personal résumé, corporate dossier, photocopies of photographs and documents, and blue drawings of portions of her work including an office building and an apartment building. Inventory available.
  - Galster, Gertrud, publications, 1963-1988, Extent: 0.5 cubic feet (Box 13)
    Architect of Denmark and member of the Union Internationale des Femmes Architectes (UIFA). Collection consists of books about women architects and reports and other literature from the meetings of the UIFA. Inventory of publications located in box. The following books were cataloged separately in the Addison library catalog, and are available through the Special Collections Reading Room: "That Exceptional One": Women in American Architecture, 1888-1988; Ziviltechnikerinnen [Civilian technicians]; Women in Danish Architecture; and Profiles: Pioneering Women Architects from Finland. Galster also has materials available on VT Imagebase. Material is in French, English, German, and Persian [?].
  - Getov, Alexandrina, drawings, 2005, 2008, Extent: 2.0 cubic feet (Oversize 21)
    Getov has a Master's of Science in Architecture from the Higher Institute of Architecture and Civil Engineering in Sofia, Bulgaria. Since 1992 she has lived in Los Angeles, California, where she is a principal at Studio Antares. This collection contains brief biographical information about Getov, as well as architectural drawings and color images of two 2005 residential projects in California.
  - Glebova, Tatiana, papers, 1990 and undated, Extent: 0.25 cubic feet (Box 14, Box 15)
    Architect of Sofia, Bulgaria. Papers consist of exhibit boards for a design she submitted to a 1990 competition and a curriculum vitae.
  - Gottwald-Thapar, Sylvia, curriculum vitae, undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Urban designer and planner at the Maryland National Capital Parks and Planning Commission. Curriculum vitae.
  - Gray, Eileen, papers, 1974-1980, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Photocopies from two short books and assorted notes and photocopied articles, 37 pages, 1974-1980
  - Griffen, Marion Mahony, article, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Article "Portrait: Marion Mahony Griffin drafting a role for women in architecture" by Thomas S. Hines in unknown publication
  - Grisogono, Ksenija, obituary, 1997, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    1909-1997. Attended Zagreb University, earned a degree in Architecture and Engineering, (1933). Attended the Institute of Fine Art in Prague, (1937). Following her studies in Prague, Grisogono studied with Le Corbusier. She worked on the Yugoslav Pavilion (1938) in Ankara, Turkey; the Italian Cultural Institute (1938) in Belgrade, Yugoslavia; and the British and French Embassies (1949), also in Belgrade. In Paris, France she worked on La Defense (1960-1970), a massive business quarter.
  - Groat, Linda N., curriculum vitae, 1996 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Associate Dean for Academic Programs and Administration at the University of Michigan. Curriculum vitae.
  - Guillissen-Hoa, Simone, biographical material, 1987, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Inventory available.
  - Hadid, Zaha, exhibit brochure, 2002, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Exhibit brochure for Iraqi born architect titled Zaha Hadid Laboratory produced by the Exhibitions Program at Yale University School of Architecture in collaboration with Zaha Hadid.
  - Hafer, Hannelore, book, 1986, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Born 1954, architect of Kassel, Germany. Collection contains a book, Glasarchitektur: Bewohnte Glashauser und Glasanbauten (1986), co-written with Egon Bohmer, and a sketch of a skyline.
  - Hahn, Ivanka Vulchanova, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Collection includes three photographs and one advertisement featuring Ganglaz Pavillon designed by Glasbau Heinrich Hahn; an exhibit catalog; and one photograph depicting a dinner or lunch at the inn in Rheinsberg [Germany] circa 1950. Material is in German.
  - Hakala-Meyer, Maija, papers, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 3)
    Born 1944. Architect of Braunschweig, Germany. Collection consists of a portfolio of photocopies of articles, architectural drawings, and photographs, and a brief biographical abstract.
  - Hanna, Bronwyn, thesis, Extent: 0.1 cu.ft. (Volume Spec Large NA1997.H36 1999)
    Active in Constructive Women: The Association of Women Architects, Landscape Architects, Planners and Women of the Building Industry. PhD thesis on early women architects in New South Wales, Australia.
  - Hansen, Fani Danadjieva, papers, 1982, 1988, 2000-2002, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    General Partner, Hansen Associates, Tiburon, California. Received Award of Honor (1980) for Design Excellence and first place for Energy Conservation Competition (1981). The collection include a résumé, Hansen Architects firm project sheets, audio interview, and information about and photographs of the Pittsburgh Civic Center. Inventory available.
  - Hautman-Kiss, Klara, papers, 1980 and undated, Extent: 0.2 cubic feet (Box 4, Box 10)
    Architect of Vienna, Austria. Papers include an article, "Residential Parks as a Solution of Today's Housing Problem;" plans for "Wiener Flur," a housing project in Vienna; a brief biography; and a pen sketch (1980) of a theatre interior.
  - Hayden, Florence Kenyon, papers, 1907 and undated, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    Architecture instructor at Ohio State University in 1905; first registered woman architect in Ohio. Papers include her class lecture notebook, with sketches; a photograph of Oxley Hall, a dormitory for women at OSU, which she designed; and a 1907 postcard addressed to her for a "20th Century" window.
  - Hebald, Margo, curriculum vitae, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    President of Margo Hebald, AIA & Associates, Inc., a company specializing in designing commercial structures and health care facilities in California. Collection consists of a brochure from her firm with a curriculum vitae.
  - Helg, Franca, article and catalog, 1989, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
  - Hermanuz, Ghislaine, biographical material, 1985, 1989, 1998, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    Born 1942. Professor of Architecture at the City College of New York School of Architecture (1986- ), Director of the City College Architectural Center, and principal of Hermanuz, Ltd., in New York. Member of the Societe d'Ingenieurs et Architectes of Switzerland. Papers consist of a résumé with a list of publications and papers; a brochure, A Housing Platform for Harlem (1985), published by the Community Design Workshop of Columbia University, of which Hermanuz was director; and a report, Shelter and Community: An Agenda for Action, (1988) prepared by Hermanuz for the United Nations Non-Governmental Organizations Committee on Shelter and Community.
  - Herrmann-Chong, Evelyn Chi-Chain, brochure, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    Born in China, 1941. Architect of Bern, Switzerland. The collection includes a brochure describes that describes the work she did as a principal of A. & C. Herrmann-Chong Freie Architekten in Bern.
  - Hillebrande, Lucy, catalog and books, 1983, 1985, 1990-1991, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    1906-1998. Architect of Gottingen, Germany. Collection includes a catalog of her 1991 exhibition and books about her work: Lucy Hillebrand--Wege Zum Raum by Klaus Hoffman (NA1088 H53 H63 1985); Lucy Hillebrand--Bauen Als Impuls und Dialog by Christian Grohn (NA1088 H53 A35 1990); and Zeit-Raume der Architektin Lucy Hillebrand by Dieter Boeminghous (NA1088 H53 A35 1983). Hillebrand's papers are in the archive of the Deutsches Architektur Museum in Frankfurt, Germany.
  - Himanen, Marina, curriculum vitae, 2011, Extent: 0.1 cu.ft. (Box 20)
    Collection includes a curriculum vitae containing a written statement by Himanen as well as several reproductions of her projects. Himanen receieved a M.Arch from Moscow Architecture Institute in 1981. She worked for a number of years in Moscow, Russia in a state design institute for hotel, resort and retail buildings before moving to Finland in 1986. In Finland, Himanen worked for Juhani Pallasmaa, SAFA, Hon. FAIA, a prominent Finnish architect and former dean of Helsinki School of Architecture at Otaniemi, who she credits with shaping her architectural vision and taste. Himanen moved to the United States in 1994 where she has worked for several architecture firms in New York.
  - Holt, Rengin, exhibition announcement, 2001, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)
    Instructor of architecture at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Framed silkscreen of Holt's "Palladio Bridge," hanging in Special Collections' Reading Room, Newman Library, and a print and an exhibition announcement.
  - Hook, Mary Rockwell, papers, 1915-1991, Extent: 0.1 cubic feet (Box 4)